<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" version="5.0" xml:lang="nb_NO">
  <info><title xml:lang="en">Contributing to FreeBSD</title>
    

    <abstract>
      <para xml:lang="en">This article describes the different ways in which an
	individual or organization may contribute to the FreeBSD
	Project.</para>
    </abstract>

    <authorgroup>
      <author xml:lang="en"><personname><firstname>Jordan</firstname><surname>Hubbard</surname></personname></author>
      <author xml:lang="en"><personname><firstname>Sam</firstname><surname>Lawrance</surname></personname></author>
      <author xml:lang="en"><personname><firstname>Mark</firstname><surname>Linimon</surname></personname></author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice xml:id="trademarks" role="trademarks">
      <para xml:lang="en">FreeBSD is a registered trademark of
  the FreeBSD Foundation.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">IEEE, POSIX, and 802 are registered
  trademarks of Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers,
  Inc. in the United States.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Many of the designations used by
  manufacturers and sellers to distinguish their products are claimed
  as trademarks.  Where those designations appear in this document,
  and the FreeBSD Project was aware of the trademark claim, the
  designations have been followed by the <quote>™</quote> or the
  <quote>®</quote> symbol.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <pubdate xml:lang="en">$FreeBSD: head/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/article.xml 52764 2019-01-13 11:00:21Z bcr $</pubdate>

    <releaseinfo xml:lang="en">$FreeBSD: head/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/article.xml 52764 2019-01-13 11:00:21Z bcr $</releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>contributing</primary></indexterm>

  <para xml:lang="en">So you want to contribute to FreeBSD? That is great!  FreeBSD
    <emphasis>relies</emphasis> on the contributions of its user base
    to survive.  Your contributions are not only appreciated, they are
    vital to FreeBSD's continued growth.</para>

  <para xml:lang="en">A large and growing number of international contributors, of
    greatly varying ages and areas of technical expertise, develop
    FreeBSD.  There is always more work to be done than there are people
    available to do it, and more help is always appreciated.</para>

  <para xml:lang="en">As a volunteer, what you do is limited only by what you want
    to do.  However, we do ask that you are aware of what other
    members of the FreeBSD community will expect of you.  You may want
    to take this into account before deciding to volunteer.</para>

  <para xml:lang="en">The FreeBSD project is responsible for an entire operating
    system environment, rather than just a kernel or a few scattered
    utilities.  As such, our <filename>TODO</filename> lists span a
    very wide range of tasks: from documentation, beta testing and
    presentation, to the system installer and highly specialized types
    of kernel development.  People of any skill level, in almost any
    area, can almost certainly help the project.</para>

  <para xml:lang="en">Commercial entities engaged in FreeBSD-related enterprises are
    also encouraged to contact us.  Do you need a special extension to
    make your product work? You will find us receptive to your
    requests, given that they are not too outlandish.  Are you working
    on a value-added product? Please let us know! We may be able to
    work cooperatively on some aspect of it.  The free software world
    is challenging many existing assumptions about how software is
    developed, sold, and maintained, and we urge you to at least give
    it a second look.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="contrib-what">
    <title xml:lang="en">What Is Needed</title>

    <para xml:lang="en">The following list of tasks and sub-projects represents
      something of an amalgam of various <filename>TODO</filename>
      lists and user requests.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="non-programmer-tasks">
      <title xml:lang="en">Ongoing Non-Programmer Tasks</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">Many people who are involved in FreeBSD are not
	programmers.  The Project includes documentation writers, Web
	designers, and support people.  All that these people need to
	contribute is an investment of time and a willingness to
	learn.</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Read through the FAQ and Handbook periodically.  If
	    anything is poorly explained, ambiguous, out of date or
            incorrect, let us know.  Even better, send us a fix
	    (Docbook is not difficult to learn, but there is no
	    objection to ASCII submissions).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Help translate FreeBSD documentation into your native
	    language.  If documentation already exists for your
	    language, you can help translate additional documents or
	    verify that the translations are up-to-date and correct.
	    First take a look at the <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/fdp-primer/translations.html">Translations
	      FAQ</link> in the FreeBSD Documentation Project Primer.
	    You are not committing yourself to translating every
	    single FreeBSD document by doing this — as a
	    volunteer, you can do as much or as little translation as
	    you desire.  Once someone begins translating, others
	    almost always join the effort.  If you only have the time
	    or energy to translate one part of the documentation,
	    please translate the installation instructions.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Read the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-questions">FreeBSD general questions mailing list</link> occasionally (or
	    even regularly).  It can be very satisfying to share your
	    expertise and help people solve their problems; sometimes
	    you may even learn something new yourself!  These forums
	    can also be a source of ideas for things to improve upon.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="ongoing-programmer-tasks">
      <title xml:lang="en">Ongoing Programmer Tasks</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">Most of the tasks listed here may require a
	considerable investment of time, an in-depth knowledge of
	the FreeBSD kernel, or both.  However, there are also many
	useful tasks which are suitable for
	<quote>weekend hackers</quote>.</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">If you run FreeBSD-CURRENT and have a good Internet
	    connection, there is a machine
	    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">current.FreeBSD.org</systemitem> which
	    builds a full release once a day—every now and
	    again, try to install the latest release from it and
	    report any failures in the process.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Read the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-bugs">FreeBSD problem reports mailing list</link>.  There may be a problem you can
	    comment constructively on or with patches you can test.
	    Or you could even try to fix one of the problems
	    yourself.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">If you know of any bug fixes which have been
	    successfully applied to -CURRENT but have not been merged
	    into -STABLE after a decent interval (normally a couple of
	    weeks), send the committer a polite reminder.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Move contributed software to
	    <filename>src/contrib</filename> in the
	    source tree.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Make sure code in
	    <filename>src/contrib</filename> is up
	    to date.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Build the source tree (or just part of it) with extra
	    warnings enabled and clean up the warnings.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Fix warnings for ports which do deprecated things like
	    using <function>gets()</function> or including
	    <filename>malloc.h</filename>.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">If you have contributed any ports and you had to make
	    FreeBSD-specific changes, send your patches back to the
	    original authors (this will make your life easier when
	    they bring out the next version).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Get copies of formal standards like <trademark class="registered">POSIX</trademark>.
	    Compare FreeBSD's behavior to that required by
	    the standard.  If the behavior differs, particularly in
	    subtle or obscure corners of the specification, send in a
	    PR about it.  If you are able, figure out how to fix it
	    and include a patch in the PR.  If you think the standard
	    is wrong, ask the standards body to consider the
	    question.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Suggest further tasks for this list!</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Work through the PR Database</title>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
	<primary>problem reports database</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/search/">FreeBSD
	  PR list</link> shows all the current active problem reports
	and requests for enhancement that have been submitted by
	FreeBSD users.  The PR database includes both programmer and
	non-programmer tasks.  Look through the open PRs, and see if
	anything there takes your interest.  Some of these might be
	very simple tasks that just need an extra pair of eyes to look
	over them and confirm that the fix in the PR is a good one.
	Others might be much more complex, or might not even have a
	fix included at all.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Start with the PRs that have not been assigned to anyone
	else.  If a PR is assigned to someone else, but it looks like
	something you can handle, email the person it is assigned to
	and ask if you can work on it—they might already have a
	patch ready to be tested, or further ideas that you can
	discuss with them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Ongoing Ports Tasks</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">The Ports Collection is a perpetual work in progress.  We
	want to provide our users with an easy to use, up to date, high
	quality repository of third party software.  We need people to
	donate some of their time and effort to help us achieve this
	goal.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Anyone can get involved, and there are lots of different
	ways to do so.  Contributing to ports is an excellent way to
	help <quote>give back</quote> something to the project.
	Whether you are looking for an ongoing role, or a fun challenge
	for a rainy day, we would love to have your help!</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">There are a number of easy ways you can contribute to
	keeping the ports tree up to date and in good working
	order:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">Find some cool or useful software and
	    <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook">create a port</link>
	    for it.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">There are a large number of ports that have no
	    maintainer.  Become a maintainer and
	    <link linkend="adopt-port">adopt a port</link>.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">If you have created or adopted a port, be
	    aware of <link linkend="maintain-port">what you need to do
	      as a maintainer</link>.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para xml:lang="en">When you are looking for a quick challenge you
	    could <link linkend="fix-broken">fix a bug or a broken
	      port</link>.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Pick one of the items from the Ideas page</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/IdeasPage">FreeBSD
	  list of projects and ideas for volunteers</link> is also
	available for people willing to contribute to the FreeBSD
	project.  The list is being regularly updated and contains
	items for both programmers and non-programmers with
	information about each project.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="contrib-how">
    <title xml:lang="en">How to Contribute</title>

    <para xml:lang="en">Contributions to the system generally fall into one or more
      of the following 5 categories:</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="contrib-general">
      <title xml:lang="en">Bug Reports and General Commentary</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">An idea or suggestion of <emphasis>general</emphasis>
	technical interest should be mailed to the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-hackers">FreeBSD technical discussions mailing list</link>.
	Likewise, people with an interest in such things (and a
	tolerance for a <emphasis>high</emphasis> volume of mail!) may
	subscribe to the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-hackers">FreeBSD technical discussions mailing list</link>.  See <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/eresources.html#ERESOURCES-MAIL">The
	  FreeBSD Handbook</link> for more information about this and
	other mailing lists.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">If you find a bug or are submitting a specific change,
	please report it using the <link xlink:href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/submit/">bug submission form</link>.
	Try to fill-in each field of the bug
	report.  Unless they exceed 65KB, include any patches directly
	in the report.  If the patch is suitable to be applied to the
	source tree put <literal>[PATCH]</literal> in the synopsis of
	the report.  When including patches,
	<emphasis>do not</emphasis> use cut-and-paste because
	cut-and-paste turns tabs into spaces and makes them unusable.
	When patches are a lot larger than 20KB, consider compressing
	them (eg. with <citerefentry><refentrytitle>gzip</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> or <citerefentry><refentrytitle>bzip2</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>) prior to
	uploading them.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">After filing a report, you should receive confirmation
	along with a tracking number.  Keep this tracking number so
	that you can update us with details about the problem.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">See also <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/problem-reports/article.html">this
	  article</link> on how to write good problem
	reports.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Changes to the Documentation</title>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
	<primary>documentation submissions</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para xml:lang="en">Changes to the documentation are overseen by the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-doc">FreeBSD documentation project mailing list</link>.
	Please look at the
	<link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/fdp-primer/index.html">FreeBSD
	  Documentation Project Primer</link> for complete
	instructions.  Send submissions and changes (even small ones
	are welcome!) using the same method as any other bug
	report.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Changes to Existing Source Code</title>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>FreeBSD-CURRENT</primary></indexterm>

      <para xml:lang="en">An addition or change to the existing source code is a
	somewhat trickier affair and depends a lot on how far out of
	date you are with the current state of FreeBSD development.
	There is a special on-going release of FreeBSD known as
	<quote>FreeBSD-CURRENT</quote> which is made available in a
	variety of ways for the convenience of developers working
	actively on the system.  See <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/current-stable.html">The FreeBSD
	  Handbook</link> for more information about getting and
	using FreeBSD-CURRENT.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Working from older sources unfortunately means that your
	changes may sometimes be too obsolete or too divergent for
	easy re-integration into FreeBSD.  Chances of this can be
	minimized somewhat by subscribing to the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-announce">FreeBSD announcements mailing list</link> and the
	<link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-current">FreeBSD-CURRENT mailing list</link> lists, where discussions on the current state of
	the system take place.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Assuming that you can manage to secure fairly up-to-date
	sources to base your changes on, the next step is to produce a
	set of diffs to send to the FreeBSD maintainers.  This is done
	with the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>diff</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> command.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The preferred <citerefentry><refentrytitle>diff</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> format for submitting patches
	is the unified output format generated by
	<command>diff -u</command>.</para>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
	<primary><command>diff</command></primary>
      </indexterm>

      <screen xml:lang="en"><prompt>%</prompt> <userinput>diff -u oldfile newfile</userinput></screen>

      <para xml:lang="en">or</para>

      <screen xml:lang="en"><prompt>%</prompt> <userinput>diff -u -r -N olddir newdir</userinput></screen>

      <para xml:lang="en">would generate a set of unified diffs for the given source
	file or directory hierarchy.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">See <citerefentry><refentrytitle>diff</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> for more information.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Once you have a set of diffs (which you may test with the
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>patch</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> command), you should submit them for inclusion
	with FreeBSD as a bug report.
	<emphasis>Do not</emphasis> just send the
	diffs to the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-hackers">FreeBSD technical discussions mailing list</link> or they will get lost! We greatly
	appreciate your submission (this is a volunteer project!);
	because we are busy, we may not be able to address it
	immediately, but it will remain in the PR database until we
	do.  Indicate your submission by including
	<literal>[PATCH]</literal> in the synopsis of the
	report.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">If you feel it appropriate (e.g. you have added, deleted,
	or renamed files), bundle your changes into a
	<command>tar</command> file.
	Archives created with <citerefentry><refentrytitle>shar</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> are also
	welcome.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">If your change is of a potentially sensitive nature, such
	as if you are unsure of copyright issues governing its further
	distribution then you should send it to Core Team <email>core@FreeBSD.org</email> directly
	rather than submitting as a bug report.  The Core Team <email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
	reaches a much smaller group of people who do much of the
	day-to-day work on FreeBSD.  Note that this group is also
	<emphasis>very busy</emphasis> and so you should only send
	mail to them where it is truly necessary.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Please refer to <citerefentry><refentrytitle>intro</refentrytitle><manvolnum>9</manvolnum></citerefentry> and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>style</refentrytitle><manvolnum>9</manvolnum></citerefentry> for
	some information on coding style.  We would appreciate it if
	you were at least aware of this information before submitting
	code.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">New Code or Major Value-Added Packages</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">In the case of a significant contribution of a large body
	work, or the addition of an important new feature to FreeBSD,
	it becomes almost always necessary to either send changes as
	tar files or upload them to a web or FTP site for
	other people to access.  If you do not have access to a web or
	FTP site, ask on an appropriate FreeBSD mailing list for
	someone to host the changes for you.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">When working with large amounts of code, the touchy
	subject of copyrights also invariably comes up.  FreeBSD
	prefers free software licenses such as BSD or ISC.
	Copyleft licenses such as GPLv2 are sometimes permitted.  The
	complete listing can be found on the <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/internal/software-license.html">core team
	licensing policy</link> page.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title xml:lang="en">Money or Hardware</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">We are always very happy to accept donations to further
	the cause of the FreeBSD Project and, in a volunteer effort
	like ours, a little can go a long way! Donations of hardware
	are also very important to expanding our list of supported
	peripherals since we generally lack the funds to buy such
	items ourselves.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="donations">
	<title xml:lang="en">Donating Funds</title>

	<para xml:lang="en">The FreeBSD Foundation is a non-profit, tax-exempt
	  foundation established to further the goals of the FreeBSD
	  Project.  As a 501(c)3 entity, the Foundation is generally
	  exempt from US federal income tax as well as Colorado State
	  income tax.  Donations to a tax-exempt entity are often
	  deductible from taxable federal income.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">Donations may be sent in check form to:
	  <address xml:lang="en">
	    The FreeBSD Foundation
	    <street>P.O. Box 20247</street>,
	    <city>Boulder</city>,
	    <state>CO</state> <postcode>80308</postcode>
	    <country>USA</country>
	  </address></para>

	<para xml:lang="en">The FreeBSD Foundation is now able to accept donations
	  through the web with PayPal.  To place a donation, please
	  visit the Foundation
	  <link xlink:href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org">web
	    site</link>.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">More information about the FreeBSD Foundation can be
	  found in <link xlink:href="https://people.FreeBSD.org/~jdp/foundation/announcement.html">The
	    FreeBSD Foundation -- an Introduction</link>.  To contact
	  the Foundation by email, write to
	  <email>info@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title xml:lang="en">Donating Hardware</title>

	<indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>donations</primary></indexterm>

	<para xml:lang="en">The FreeBSD Project happily accepts donations of
	  hardware that it can find good use for.  If you are
	  interested in donating hardware, please contact the
	  <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/donations/">Donations Liaison
	    Office</link>.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="ports-contributing">
    <title xml:lang="en">Contributing to ports</title>

    <sect2 xml:id="adopt-port">
      <title xml:lang="en">Adopting an unmaintained port</title>

      <sect3>
	<title xml:lang="en">Choosing an unmaintained port</title>

	<para xml:lang="en">Taking over maintainership of ports that are
	  unmaintained is a great way to get involved.  Unmaintained
	  ports are only updated and fixed when somebody volunteers to
	  work on them.  There are a large number of unmaintained
	  ports.  It is a good idea to start with adopting a port that
	  you use regularly.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">Unmaintained ports have their
	  <varname>MAINTAINER</varname> set to
	  <literal>ports@FreeBSD.org</literal>.  A list of unmaintained
	  ports and their current errors and problem reports can be seen
	  at the <link xlink:href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/portsconcordanceformaintainer.py?maintainer=ports%40FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD
	    Ports Monitoring System</link>.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">Some ports affect a large number of others due to
	  dependencies and slave port relationships.  Generally, we
	  want people to have some experience before they maintain such
	  ports.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">You can find out whether or not a port has dependencies
	  or slave ports by looking at a master index of ports called
	  <filename>INDEX</filename>.  (The name of the file varies
	  by release of FreeBSD; for instance,
	  <filename>INDEX-8</filename>.) Some ports have conditional
	  dependencies that are not included in a default
	  <filename>INDEX</filename> build.  We expect you to be able to
	  recognize such ports by looking through other ports'
	  <filename>Makefile</filename>s.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title xml:lang="en">How to adopt the port</title>

	<para xml:lang="en">First make sure you understand your
	  <link linkend="maintain-port">responsibilities as a
	    maintainer</link>.  Also read the
	  <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook">Porter's
	    Handbook</link>.  <emphasis>Please do not commit yourself
	    to more than you feel you can comfortably
	    handle.</emphasis></para>

	<para xml:lang="en">You may request maintainership of any unmaintained port
	  as soon as you wish.  Simply set <varname>MAINTAINER</varname>
	  to your own email address and send a PR (Problem Report) with
	  the change.  If the port has build errors or needs updating,
	  you may wish to include any other changes in the same PR.
	  This will help because many committers are less willing to
	  assign maintainership to someone who does not have a known
	  track record with FreeBSD.  Submitting PRs that fix build errors
	  or update ports are the best ways to establish one.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">File your PR with category <literal>ports</literal> and
	  class <literal>change-request</literal>.  A committer will
	  examine your PR, commit the changes, and finally close the
	  PR.  Sometimes this process can take a little while
	  (committers are volunteers, too :).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="maintain-port">
      <title xml:lang="en">The challenge for port maintainers</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">This section will give you an idea of why ports need to be
	maintained and outline the responsibilities of a port
	maintainer.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="why-maintenance">
	<title xml:lang="en">Why ports require maintenance</title>

	<para xml:lang="en">Creating a port is a once-off task.  Ensuring that a
	  port is up to date and continues to build and run requires
	  an ongoing maintenance effort.  Maintainers are the people
	  who dedicate some of their time to meeting these goals.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">The foremost reason ports need maintenance is to bring
	  the latest and greatest in third party software to the FreeBSD
	  community.  An additional challenge is to keep individual
	  ports working within the Ports Collection framework as it
	  evolves.</para>

	<para xml:lang="en">As a maintainer, you will need to manage the following
	  challenges:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">New software versions and updates.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">New versions and updates of existing ported
		software become available all the time, and these need
		to be incorporated into the Ports Collection in order
		to provide up-to-date software.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Changes to dependencies.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If significant changes are made to the dependencies
		of your port, it may need to be updated so that it will
		continue to work correctly.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Changes affecting dependent ports.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If other ports depend on a port that you maintain,
		changes to your port may require coordination with
		other maintainers.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Interaction with other users, maintainers and
		developers.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Part of being a maintainer is taking on a support
		role.  You are not expected to provide general support
		(but we welcome it if you choose to do so).  What you
		should provide is a point of coordination for
		FreeBSD-specific issues regarding your ports.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Bug hunting.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">A port may be affected by bugs which are specific
		to FreeBSD.  You will need to investigate, find, and fix
		these bugs when they are reported.  Thoroughly testing
		a port to identify problems before they make their way
		into the Ports Collection is even better.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Changes to ports infrastructure and policy.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Occasionally the systems that are used to build
		ports and packages are updated or a new recommendation
		affecting the infrastructure is made.  You should be
		aware of these changes in case your ports are affected
		and require updating.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Changes to the base system.</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">FreeBSD is under constant development.  Changes to
		software, libraries, the kernel or even policy changes
		can cause flow-on change requirements to ports.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title xml:lang="en">Maintainer responsibilities</title>

	<sect4>
	  <title xml:lang="en">Keep your ports up to date</title>

	  <para xml:lang="en">This section outlines the process to follow to keep your
	    ports up to date.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">This is an overview.  More information about upgrading a
	    port is available in the
	    <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook">
	      Porter's Handbook</link>.</para>

	  <procedure>
	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Watch for updates</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Monitor the upstream vendor for new versions,
		updates and security fixes for the software.
		Announcement mailing lists or news web pages are useful
		for doing this.  Sometimes users will contact you and
		ask when your port will be updated.  If you are busy
		with other things or for any reason just cannot update
		it at the moment, ask if they will help you by
		submitting an update.</para>

	      <para xml:lang="en">You may also receive automated email from the
		<literal>FreeBSD Ports Version Check</literal> informing
		you that a newer version of your port's distfile is
		available.  More information about that system
		(including how to stop future emails) will be provided
		in the message.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Incorporate changes</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">When they become available, incorporate the changes
		into the port.  You need to be able to generate a patch
		between the original port and your updated port.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Review and test</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Thoroughly review and test your changes:</para>

	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Build, install and test your port on as many
		    platforms and architectures as you can.  It is
		    common for a port to work on one branch or platform
		    and fail on another.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Make sure your port's dependencies are complete.
		    The recommended way of doing this is by installing
		    your own ports <application>tinderbox</application>.
		    See <link linkend="resources">resources</link>
		    for more information.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Check that the packing list is up to date.  This
		    involves adding in any new files and directories and
		    removing unused entries.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Verify your port using <citerefentry vendor="ports"><refentrytitle>portlint</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> as a
		    guide.  See <link linkend="resources">resources</link> for important
		    information about using
		    <application>portlint</application>.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Consider whether changes to your port might
		    cause any other ports to break.  If this is the
		    case, coordinate the changes with the maintainers of
		    those ports.  This is especially important if your
		    update changes the shared library version; in this
		    case, at the very least, the dependent ports will
		    need to get a <varname>PORTREVISION</varname> bump
		    so that they will automatically be upgraded by
		    automated tools such as
		    <application>portmaster</application> or
		    <citerefentry vendor="ports"><refentrytitle>portupgrade</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Submit changes</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Send your update by submitting a PR with an
		explanation of the changes and a patch containing the
		differences between the original port and the updated
		one.  Please refer to <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/problem-reports">Writing FreeBSD
		  Problem Reports</link> for information on how to
		write a really good PR.</para>

	      <note>
		<para xml:lang="en">Please do not submit a <citerefentry><refentrytitle>shar</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> archive of the
		  entire port; instead, use <citerefentry><refentrytitle>diff</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
		  <literal>-ruN</literal>.  In this way, committers can
		  much more easily see exactly what changes are being
		  made.  The Porter's Handbook section on <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook/port-upgrading.html">Upgrading</link>
		  has more information.</para>
	      </note>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Wait</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">At some stage a committer will deal with your PR.
		It may take minutes, or it may take weeks — so
		please be patient.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Give feedback</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If a committer finds a problem with your changes,
		they will most likely refer it back to you.  A prompt
		response will help get your PR committed faster, and
		is better for maintaining a thread of conversation
		when trying to resolve any problems.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">And Finally</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Your changes will be committed and your port will
		have been updated.  The PR will then be closed by the
		committer.  That's it!</para>
	    </step>
	  </procedure>
	</sect4>

	<sect4>
	  <title xml:lang="en">Ensure your ports continue to build correctly</title>

	  <para xml:lang="en">This section is about discovering and fixing problems
	    that stop your ports from building correctly.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">FreeBSD only guarantees that the Ports Collection works on
	    the <literal>-STABLE</literal> branches.
	    In
	    theory, you should be able to get by with running the latest
	    release of each stable branch (since the ABIs are not
	    supposed to change) but if you can run the branch, that is
	    even better.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">Since the majority of FreeBSD installations run on
	    PC-compatible machines (what is termed the
	    <literal>i386</literal> architecture), we expect you to keep
	    the port working on that architecture.  We prefer that ports
	    also work on the <literal>amd64</literal> architecture
	    running native.  It is completely fair to ask for help if
	    you do not have one of these machines.</para>

	  <note>
	    <para xml:lang="en">The usual failure modes for
	      non-<literal>x86</literal> machines are that the original
	      programmers assumed that, for instance, pointers are
	      <literal>int</literal>s, or that a relatively lax older
	      <application>gcc</application> compiler was being used.
	      More and more, application authors are reworking their
	      code to remove these assumptions — but if the author
	      is not actively maintaining their code, you may need to do
	      this yourself.</para>
	  </note>

	  <para xml:lang="en">These are the tasks you need to perform to ensure your
	    port is able to be built:</para>

	  <procedure>
	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Watch for build failures</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Check your mail for mail from
		<literal>pkg-fallout@FreeBSD.org</literal> 
		and the <link xlink:href="http://portscout.FreeBSD.org">distfiles scanner</link>
		to see if any of the port which are failing to build
		are out of date.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Collect information</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Once you are aware of a problem, collect information
		to help you fix it.  Build errors reported by
		<literal>pkg-fallout</literal> are accompanied by logs
		which will show you where the build failed.  If the
		failure was reported to you by a user, ask them to send
		you information which may help in diagnosing the
		problem, such as:</para>

	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Build logs</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">The commands and options used to build the
		    port (including options set in
		    <filename>/etc/make.conf</filename>)</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">A list of packages installed on their system
		    as shown by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pkg-info</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">The version of FreeBSD they are running as
		    shown by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>uname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry><command> -a</command></para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">When their ports collection was last
		    updated</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">When their ports tree and
		  <filename>INDEX</filename> was last updated</para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Investigate and find a solution</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Unfortunately there is no straightforward process to
		follow to do this.  Remember, though: if you are stuck,
		ask for help!  The <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-ports">FreeBSD ports mailing list</link> is a good place to start,
		and the upstream developers are often very
		helpful.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Submit changes</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Just as with updating a port, you should now
		incorporate changes, review and test, submit your
		changes in a PR, and provide feedback if
		required.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Send patches to upstream authors</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">In some cases, you will have to make patches to the
		port to make it run on FreeBSD.  Some (but not all)
		upstream authors will accept such patches back into
		their code for the next release.  If so, this may even
		help their users on other BSD-based systems as well and
		perhaps save duplicated effort.  Please consider sending
		any applicable patches to the authors as a
		courtesy.</para>
	    </step>
	  </procedure>
	</sect4>

	<sect4>

	  <title xml:lang="en">Investigate bug reports and PRs related to your
	    port</title>

	  <para xml:lang="en">This section is about discovering and fixing
	    bugs.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">FreeBSD-specific bugs are generally caused by assumptions
	    about the build and runtime environments that do not apply
	    to FreeBSD.  You are less likely to encounter a problem of this
	    type, but it can be more subtle and difficult to
	    diagnose.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">These are the tasks you need to perform to ensure your
	    port continues to work as intended:</para>

	  <procedure>
	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Respond to bug reports</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Bugs may be reported to you through email via the
		<link xlink:href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/search/">
		Problem Report database</link>.  Bugs may also be
		reported directly to you by users.</para>

	      <para xml:lang="en">You should respond to PRs and other reports within
		14 days, but please try not to take that long.  Try to
		respond as soon as possible, even if it is just to say
		you need some more time before you can work on the
		PR.</para>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If you have not responded after 14 days, any
		committer may commit from a PR that you have not
		responded to via a
		<literal>maintainer-timeout</literal>.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Collect information</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If the person reporting the bug has not also
		provided a fix, you need to collect the information that
		will allow you to generate one.</para>

	      <para xml:lang="en">If the bug is reproducible, you can collect most of
		the required information yourself.  If not, ask the
		person who reported the bug to collect the information
		for you, such as:</para>

	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">A detailed description of their actions,
		    expected program behavior and actual behavior</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Copies of input data used to trigger the
		    bug</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Information about their build and execution
		    environment — for example, a list of installed
		    packages and the output of <citerefentry><refentrytitle>env</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Core dumps</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para xml:lang="en">Stack traces</para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Eliminate incorrect reports</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Some bug reports may be incorrect.  For example,
		the user may have simply misused the program; or their
		installed packages may be out of date and require
		updating.  Sometimes a reported bug is not specific to
		FreeBSD.  In this case report the bug to the upstream
		developers.  If the bug is within your capabilities to
		fix, you can also patch the port so that the fix is
		applied before the next upstream release.</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Find a solution</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">As with build errors, you will need to sort out a
		fix to the problem.  Again, remember to ask if you are
		stuck!</para>
	    </step>

	    <step>
	      <title xml:lang="en">Submit or approve changes</title>

	      <para xml:lang="en">Just as with updating a port, you should now
		incorporate changes, review and test, and submit your
		changes in a PR (or send a follow-up if a PR already
		exists for the problem).  If another user has submitted
		changes in the PR, you can also send a follow-up saying
		whether or not you approve the changes.</para>
	    </step>
	  </procedure>
	</sect4>

	<sect4>
	  <title xml:lang="en">Providing support</title>

	  <para xml:lang="en">Part of being a maintainer is providing support —
	    not for the software in general — but for the port and
	    any FreeBSD-specific quirks and problems.  Users may contact
	    you with questions, suggestions, problems and patches.  Most
	    of the time their correspondence will be specific to
	    FreeBSD.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">Occasionally you may have to invoke your skills in
	    diplomacy, and kindly point users seeking general support to
	    the appropriate resources.  Less frequently you will
	    encounter a person asking why the <literal>RPM</literal>s
	    are not up to date or how can they get the software to run
	    under Foo Linux.  Take the opportunity to tell them that
	    your port is up to date (if it is, of course!), and suggest
	    that they try FreeBSD.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">Sometimes users and developers will decide that you are
	    a busy person whose time is valuable and do some of the work
	    for you.  For example, they might:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para xml:lang="en">submit a PR or send you patches to update your
		port,</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para xml:lang="en">investigate and perhaps provide a fix to a PR,
		or</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para xml:lang="en">otherwise submit changes to your port.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <para xml:lang="en">In these cases your main obligation is to respond in a
	    timely manner.  Again, the timeout for non-responsive
	    maintainers is 14 days.  After this period changes may be
	    committed unapproved.  They have taken the trouble to do
	    this for you; so please try to at least respond promptly.
	    Then review, approve, modify or discuss their changes with
	    them as soon as possible.</para>

	  <para xml:lang="en">If you can make them feel that their contribution is
	    appreciated (and it should be) you will have a better chance
	    persuading them to do more things for you in the future
	    <!-- smiley -->:-).</para>
	</sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="fix-broken">
      <title xml:lang="en">Finding and fixing a broken port</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">There are two really good places to find a port that needs
	some attention.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">You can use the <link xlink:href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/search">web
	  interface</link> to the Problem Report database to search
	through and view unresolved PRs.  The majority of ports PRs are
	updates, but with a little searching and skimming over synopses
	you should be able to find something interesting to work on (the
	<literal>sw-bug</literal> class is a good place to
	start).</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The other place is the <link xlink:href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/">FreeBSD Ports Monitoring
	  System</link>.  In particular look for unmaintained ports
	with build errors and ports that are marked
	<varname>BROKEN</varname>.  It is OK to send changes for a
	maintained port as well, but remember to ask the maintainer in
	case they are already working on the problem.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">Once you have found a bug or problem, collect information,
	investigate and fix!  If there is an existing PR, follow up to
	that.  Otherwise create a new PR.  Your changes will be reviewed
	and, if everything checks out, committed.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mortal-coil">
      <title xml:lang="en">When to call it quits</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">As your interests and commitments change, you may find that
	you no longer have time to continue some (or all) of your ports
	contributions.  That is fine!  Please let us know if you are no
	longer using a port or have otherwise lost time or interest in
	being a maintainer.  In this way we can go ahead and allow other
	people to try to work on existing problems with the port without
	waiting for your response.  Remember, FreeBSD is a volunteer
	project, so if maintaining a port is no fun any more, it is
	probably time to let someone else do it!</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">In any case, the Ports Management Team
	(<literal>portmgr</literal>) reserves the right to reset your
	maintainership if you have not actively maintained your port in
	some time.  (Currently, this is set to 3 months.)  By this, we
	mean that there are unresolved problems or pending updates that
	have not been worked on during that time.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="resources">
      <title xml:lang="en">Resources for ports maintainers and contributors</title>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook">Porter's
	  Handbook</link> is your hitchhiker's guide to the ports
	system.  Keep it handy!</para>

      <para xml:lang="en"><link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/problem-reports">Writing FreeBSD
	  Problem Reports</link> describes how to best formulate and
	submit a PR.  In 2005 more than eleven thousand ports PRs were
	submitted!  Following this article will greatly assist us in
	reducing the time needed to handle your PRs.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/query.cgi">
	  Problem Report database</link>.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/">FreeBSD Ports
	  Monitoring System</link> can show you cross-referenced
	information about ports such as build errors and problem
	reports.  If you are a maintainer you can use it to check on the
	build status of your ports.  As a contributor you can use it to
	find broken and unmaintained ports that need to be fixed.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="http://portscout.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD Ports
	  distfile scanner</link> can show you ports for which the
	distfiles are not fetchable.  You can check on your own ports or
	use it to find ports that need their
	<varname>MASTER_SITES</varname> updated.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en"><package>ports-mgmt/poudriere</package> is the most
	thorough way to test a port through the entire cycle of
	installation, packaging, and deinstallation.
	Documentation is located at the 
	<link xlink:href="https://github.com/freebsd/poudriere">
	  poudriere github repository</link></para>

      <para xml:lang="en"><citerefentry vendor="ports"><refentrytitle>portlint</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> is an application which can be used to
	verify that your port conforms to many important stylistic and
	functional guidelines.  <application>portlint</application> is a
	simple heuristic application, so you should use it
	<emphasis>only as a guide</emphasis>.  If
	<application>portlint</application> suggests changes which seem
	unreasonable, consult the <link xlink:href="@@URL_RELPREFIX@@/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook">Porter's Handbook</link>
	or ask for advice.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-ports">FreeBSD ports mailing list</link> is for general ports-related discussion.  It
	is a good place to ask for help.  You can <link xlink:href="https://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo">subscribe, or
	  read and search the list archives</link>.  Reading the
	archives of the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-ports-bugs">FreeBSD ports bugs mailing list</link> and the <link xlink:href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/svn-ports-head">SVN commit messages for the ports tree for head/</link> may also be
	of interest.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="ideas-contributing">
    <title xml:lang="en">Getting Started in Other Areas</title>

    <para xml:lang="en">Looking for something interesting to get started that is not
      mentioned elsewhere in this article?  The FreeBSD Project has
      several Wiki pages containing areas within which new
      contributors can get ideas on how to get started.</para>

    <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/JuniorJobs">Junior
	Jobs</link> page has a list of projects that might be of
      interest to people just getting started in FreeBSD, and want to
      work on interesting things to get their feet wet.</para>

    <para xml:lang="en">The <link xlink:href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/IdeasPage">Ideas
	Page</link> contains various "nice to have" or
      "interesting" things to work on in the Project.</para>
  </sect1>

  <index/>
</article>
